<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The foundation of popery shaken, or, The Bishop of Rome's supremacy opposed in a sermon upon Matth. XVI. 18, 19 / by William Cade.</title>
            <author>Cade, William, 1651 or 2-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C194</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24760</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08483064</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08483064</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41377</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31666)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41377)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1248:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The foundation of popery shaken, or, The Bishop of Rome's supremacy opposed in a sermon upon Matth. XVI. 18, 19 / by William Cade.</title>
                  <author>Cade, William, 1651 or 2-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M. for Robert Clavel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: The foundation shaken, or, The pope's supremacy opposed.</note>
                  <note>Errata: Verso of t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XVI, 18-19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:41377:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41377:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41377:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Geo. Thorp. <hi>R<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> in C. P. &amp; D. D<hi rend="sup">no.</hi>
                  </hi> Gulielmo <hi>Archiep. Cant. a Sacris Domeſticis.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nov.</hi> 4th. 1678.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41377:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FOUNDATION OF <hi>Popery Shaken:</hi> OR, THE Biſhop of <hi>ROME'S</hi> Supremacy Oppoſed.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON, UPON <hi>MATTH.</hi> XVI. 18, 19.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Cade,</hi> M. A. and Prieſt of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.M.</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> at the Signe of the <hi>Peacock,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s-Church-yard, 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:41377:3"/>
            <head>ERRORS of the PRESS.</head>
            <p>PAge 5. line 11. for <hi>for,</hi> read <hi>of.</hi> p. 8. l. 7. f. <hi>or,</hi> r. <hi>and</hi> p. 10. l. 9. r. <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> ibid. l. 12. r. <hi>Labours.</hi> p. 21. l. 24. r. <hi>Aethiopia.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41377:3"/>
            <head>TO Mr. Edward Muns OF CLAPHAM, IN THE County of <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RREY,</hi> Gent.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Reverend <hi>Clergy-Man</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> affirms, That when the Publick Maintenance of any Tenet will bring the utmoſt Hazard upon a Man<hi>'s</hi> Life or Fortune, and there be a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, that that <hi>Doctrine</hi> ſhould be propagated; Then to be ſilent upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Worldly Conceits of Honour, Profit, or preſent Safety, is a Breach of <hi>Chriſtian Duty;</hi> or at leaſt, it argues a Cowardize, unbecoming One that hath not only Liſted himſelf under <hi>Chriſt's Banners,</hi> but hath undertaken the Charge of his <hi>Flock;</hi> which he muſt not Deſert, when the <hi>Wolfe</hi> approaches.</p>
            <p>I do not hence urge a Neceſſity of Printing this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or that every <hi>Church-Man</hi> is obliged to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his Judgement concerning the Subject treated
<pb facs="tcp:41377:4"/>of in it: But I would have it rather Received as an Excuſe for the Publiſhing this Diſcourſe; to which I was not only Invited, but Commanded, by ſome that heard it Preached; who were likewiſe inſtant in the fore-going Argument.</p>
            <p>I cannot preſume, it will do that Service, which thoſe Friends in Kindneſs ſeemed to imagine: What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their Motive was to the Publication, Obedience to their Commands, and Complyance with their Deſires, were mine.</p>
            <p>It was not deſigned, neither can a <hi>Sermon</hi> be thought, to be a full <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> and a ſufficient <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> in that particular Matter: I am ſatisfyed, if it give but Hints to thoſe that have time to look more into the <hi>Subject,</hi> and ſupply the Wants of thoſe that have not Leiſure and Opportunity to do ſo.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Church</hi> is ſet on Fire, and like to be conſumed in the Flames, 'tis enough for me, if I can bring but one Drop of Water towards the quenching it. When the <hi>Fence</hi> is broken down, and the Vine, that <hi>God's</hi> own Right Hand hath Planted amongſt us, is like to be Trodden down by the <hi>Wild Boar</hi> of the <hi>Forreſt;</hi> I am not ſo vain, as to think I am able to Repair it: I only diſcover my Willingneſs, by putting to my Helping Hand.</p>
            <p>Tho all <hi>Diviſions</hi> are Deſtructive to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> yet the <hi>Popiſh Faction</hi> ſeems to tend directly to its Ruin; as being formed under one <hi>Head,</hi> and having a more United Intereſt than any other: Would the other <hi>Parties</hi> conſider how much they aſſiſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in Rending and Dividing our <hi>Church;</hi> would they be ſenſible, how much our own
<pb facs="tcp:41377:4"/>
               <hi>Diviſions</hi> Encourage the <hi>Foe,</hi> they would no longer, for a few ſlight Circumſtances, ſtand at Variance with their <hi>Mother Church;</hi> but would Unite againſt the <hi>Common Enemy.</hi> It is a <hi>Maxime</hi> in their <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> which all our <hi>Separations</hi> help them to put into Practice: And 'tis to be feared, that we have more Cauſe to Fear, than the <hi>Jews</hi> had; That the <hi>Romans</hi> will come, and take away our Place and Nation. For, as that <hi>Party</hi> is Inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to us, were we United; ſo 'tis very Dangerous by our <hi>Diviſions.</hi> It is <hi>Courage</hi> not to Fear, and <hi>Prudence</hi> not to Slight, an <hi>Enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis to be feared, That if we thus go on, <hi>Tacitus's</hi> Obſervation of the <hi>Britains,</hi> will be very Applicable to us at this juncture; That their <hi>Differences</hi> at Home not ſuffering them to Unite, they were all O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by the <hi>Romans; Dum Singuli pugnabant Omnes vincebantur.</hi> And we know who ſaid; <hi>A Kingdom or Houſe divided againſt it ſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>Enemy</hi> is before the Gates, and ſets up His <hi>Batteries</hi> againſt our Walls; Whoever opens a <hi>Poſtern,</hi> or pulls down our Inward Fortifications, does more Miſchief to us, than we can apprehend from the <hi>Foe</hi> Without: Were our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a <hi>City</hi> at Unity within it ſelf, we need not fear the <hi>Armies</hi> of the <hi>Baylonians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> While an Honeſt <hi>Zeal</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> was thus prevailing with me, to publiſh this <hi>Sermon;</hi> I more willingly complyed there-with, as laying hold of it, as a Means of owning to the World, what high <hi>Obligations</hi> have been laid on me, by your Generous and Bountifull Hand; A Private <hi>Gratitude</hi> would
<pb facs="tcp:41377:5"/>no longer content me, when I had an Opportunity of making it Publick.</p>
            <p>If <hi>You</hi> accept of theſe my firſt Endeavours, I ſhall not much value the Opinion of <hi>Others,</hi> nor fear the Cenſures of an <hi>Envious World:</hi> The <hi>Preſent</hi> is indeed Mean, like all the Returns of the <hi>Poor</hi> to their <hi>Benefactours;</hi> But I hope, it will be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as coming from an Humble and Thankful <hi>Heart. You</hi> have a juſt Right and Title not only to the <hi>Author,</hi> but to whatever ſhall be produced by him; as being the onely <hi>Perſon,</hi> to whom he owes all the Advantages of his <hi>Education.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are other <hi>Reaſons,</hi> that render this <hi>Your Due,</hi> who are ſo conſtant to your <hi>Profeſſion;</hi> and even in <hi>Clapham,</hi> are ſo Zealous for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> May <hi>You</hi> Live long, to ſee <hi>Her</hi> Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and Tread down all her <hi>Enemies: You</hi> ſaw <hi>Her</hi> once under a Cloud; and even then, ſhe Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and by <hi>Her Patience</hi> in Sufferings, triumpht over her <hi>Perſecutors;</hi> May <hi>She</hi> now Exalt <hi>Her-ſelf</hi> in the midst of her <hi>Adverſaries</hi> round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Her;</hi> and become (as <hi>She</hi> is the Glory of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> ſo) a <hi>Terror</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> And may <hi>You</hi> long continue a Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Member</hi> of <hi>Her</hi> here, while <hi>She</hi> is <hi>Militant,</hi> that <hi>You</hi> may be a part of <hi>Her,</hi> when <hi>She</hi> ſhall be <hi>Triumphant:</hi> This is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Obedient Kinſman, and Humble Servant, William Cade.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41377:5"/>
            <head>THE Foundation Shaken: OR, The <hi>Popes Supremacy</hi> Oppoſed.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mat. xvi. 18, 19.</hi>
                     </bibl> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>And I ſay unto thee, thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> and upon this Rock will I Build my Church; and the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail against it.</p>
                  <p>And I will give unto thee the Keyes of the Kingdom of Heaven: And whatſoever thou ſhalt Bind on Earth, ſhall be Bound in Heaven; And whatſoever thou ſhalt Looſe on Earth, ſhall be Looſed in Heaven.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THat this Text is perverted, for the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Pope's Supremacy over the whole Chriſtian Church, as being ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on two weak Foundations: The One, That St. <hi>Peter</hi> is hereby conſtituted Oecumenical Paſtor; The Other, That the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is herein St. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor, and enjoys all his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41377:6"/>ſuppoſed Priviledges, is ſo Notoriouſly Known, that having but read the Words, I am concerned to vindicate them from that perverted ſenſe, and to diſcover the full meaning and deſign of the place; whereby I ſhall wreſt this Scripture out of their Hands, and render it Unſerviceable to their Cauſe. And this I ſhall endeavour to do by this following Method.</p>
            <p n="1">I. I ſhall propoſe the Interpretation, which the Advocates for the Pope's Supremacy put on theſe Words.</p>
            <p n="2">II. I ſhall give the True Senſe of the Words, and explain the meaning of every particular Phraſe in the Text, and thereby Anſwer all that is mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial in their Interpretation.</p>
            <p n="3">III. I ſhall conſider the Power, Authority, and Priviledges hereby conferred on St. <hi>Peter,</hi> which are either
<list>
                  <item>1. Extraordinary, or Perſonal.</item>
                  <item>2. Ordinary, or to be derived down to his Succeſſors; in which latter Branch, I ſhall endeavour to Refute the Supremacy of the Pope, as it is pretendedly Supported there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. I begin with the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Gloſs and Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.
<note place="margin">Cajetan <hi>in locum.</hi>
               </note> The firſt I meet with, is Cardinal <hi>Caje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>'s literal Expoſition: In which we need not doubt to find the Doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: ſince he profeſſes in his Epiſtle to Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 7th, that he ſubmits it to the Apoſtolical Seat; and that he accounts it not ſafe to Write any thing but what agrees thereto. <hi>Thou Art,</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>and not only art Called, a Rock; and to this purpoſe thou
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41377:6"/>art ſuch, that thou maiſt be the Foundation of the Church.</hi> And the Pronoun <hi>This,</hi> ſhews the Rock of which it is ſpoken; for of no other is it ſaid, either Before or After, that it is a <hi>Rock,</hi> but of <hi>Peter:</hi> As if Chriſt had plainly ſaid, <hi>Thou art a Rock; and upon this Rock, I will lay the Foundation of my Church:</hi> Whereby he promiſes the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Church to <hi>Peter;</hi> ſince he was to be the ſame in the Church, as the Foundation is in the Building. So that Chriſt appointed his Church to be Supported and Suſteined upon the Strength of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Seat; <hi>Againſt which, the Gates of Hell ſhould not prevail.</hi> But he proceeds; <hi>I will give thee:</hi> Now he promiſes, after his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection</hi> he gave; as <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.15, <hi>&amp;c. Feed my Sheep:</hi> Which Text, whether it prove what it is produced for, it is not my Buſineſs at preſent to enquire. Upon the Word <hi>Keyes,</hi> he tells us; That Chriſt by many Metaphors deſcribes and explains the Supremacy of <hi>Peter:</hi> As before, by the Foundation in a Building; ſo now, by the Reſemblances of <hi>Keyes.</hi> For it is obſervable, That when Princes come firſt to their Crowns, or by Conqueſt gain new Towns; the Keys are preſented to them, in Acknowledgment of their Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: In Conformity to which Cuſtome, Chriſt promiſes, That he will give <hi>Peter</hi> the Keyes; and thereby, the Primacy in his Church. And he adds, That it is ſaid <hi>Keyes,</hi> in the Plural Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; becauſe the Supream Power conſiſts of two things: One is the Power of Diſcerning, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Defining thoſe Things that belong to the Kingdom of Heaven; and this is called, <hi>The
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41377:7"/>Key of Knowledge:</hi> The Other, is the Power of Doing and Executing what is ſo Defined; and this is called, <hi>The Key of Power.</hi> What follows concerning the Kingdom of Heaven, limits St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Power to Spirituals; not admitting it in Temporals, unleſs in <hi>Ordine ad Spiritualia;</hi> As his Note afterwards, upon <hi>Super Terram,</hi> denyes St. <hi>Peter</hi> to have any Authority in <hi>Purgatory:</hi> But theſe things concern not us; let them Diſpute them amongſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>The next Aſſertor of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Supremacy, and conſequently a Corrupter of this Text,
<note place="margin">Bell. <hi>de Pont.</hi> Rom. <hi>cap. x. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> is <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine;</hi> who, when he had concluded, that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy is the beſt ſort of Government in the Church, (as indeed it is, if all things be ſubjected to the Scepter of Chriſt) proceeds to prove, That St. <hi>Peter</hi> had this Power committed to him by this Place: For (ſayes he) this Power is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to him by this Double Metaphor: The Firſt is of a Foundation; becauſe the ſame as a Foundation is to the Edifice, that the Head is to the Body, a Governour to his City, a King to his Subjects, and a Father of a Family to his Houſe. The other Metaphor of Keys ſignifies thus much: That to whomſoever the Keys are delivered, the ſame is appointed King or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the City; who may Admit, or Exclude, whom he pleaſes. And he very peremptorily calls them Hereticks, who will not grant <hi>Peter</hi> to be the Rock; nor by the Metaphors of the Foundation, and of the Keys, will allow Chief and Soveraign Eccleſiaſtical Authority to be given.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:41377:7"/>
            <p> Concerning the <hi>Rock,</hi> he ſayes, There are Four Opinions: The Firſt, that of the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> as they call themſelves, excluding us; That it is <hi>Peter;</hi> not as a Particular Perſon, but as Paſtor, and Head of the Church. The Second is, <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> his; That the <hi>Rock</hi> is every Faithful Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. The Third is <hi>Calvin</hi>'s; That the <hi>Rock</hi> is Chriſt. The Fourth is <hi>Luther</hi>'s; That the <hi>Rock</hi> is the Faith of <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Confeſſion that he but now made.</p>
            <p>As a Proof for the Firſt of theſe, he tells us, That <hi>Cephas</hi> in the <hi>Syriack,</hi> is <hi>Peter,</hi> and a <hi>Rock</hi> too: In <hi>Greek,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifie the ſame thing. In Confirmation of it alſo, he brings the Teſtimony of many Fathers, whoſe Senſe is ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctrine; That the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Cauſe is quite deſtroyed, if they may be Judges; as in due Place ſhall be ſeen.</p>
            <p>I am not ſo much concerned for <hi>Eraſmus</hi>'s Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, as to enter the Liſts for it: But let it paſs with the ſame Remark that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth; That if every Chriſtian were the Foundation, where were the Building?</p>
            <p>When I come to give the true Meaning of my Text, I ſhall ſhew, that both <hi>Calvin</hi>'s and <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>'s Senſe may be admitted: And that either of Them is a ſafer and truer Expoſition of this Text, than what they produce; and doth ſtand Confirmed by the Authority of Antient Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal underſtands by the Power of the Keys, Supreme Power over all the Church; which he endeavours to prove out of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 22.22.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41377:8"/>
               <hi>The Key of the Houſe of</hi> David <hi>will I lay upon his Shoulder: So he ſhall Open, and none ſhall Shut; and he ſhall Shut, and none ſhall Open.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Power (he ſayes) is ſo given to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as not to be kept by him alone; but to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to other Paſtors, by his Authority. But as to the Extent of the Power of the Keys, it is not agreed upon betwixt <hi>Cajetan</hi> &amp; <hi>Bellarmine;</hi> The latter of which, quarrels with the Other for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven, are not the ſame thing with the Power of Bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Looſing; But that the Keys contain ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beſide Order and Juriſdiction: Which Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> obſerves) is more Subtle than True.</p>
            <p>What is wanting in theſe two Cardinals for the ſupport of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Primacy, is ſupply'd by <hi>Stapleton</hi> and the <hi>Rhemiſh</hi> Interpreters; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider whoſe Gloſſes I now proceed: In theſe words, ſays <hi>Stapleton, Upon this Rock will I build my Church;</hi> Chriſt declares the Reaſon why he gave <hi>Simon</hi> the Name of <hi>Peter,</hi> becauſe he was to be the Rock on which the whole Church was to be Built. The building of the Church is not given, but promiſed; The Church is ſaid to be built, when it is Gathered, Fed, Taught, and Ruled; and when any Member is anew added to it, or reconciled. But in all this manner of buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or gathering the Faithful into one Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; The other Paſtors are VVorkmen, and wiſe Architects, but <hi>Peter</hi> the Maſter of the Family; the reſt are Pillars, <hi>Peter</hi> the Foundation on which they rely: He allows Chriſt to be called
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41377:8"/>in Scripture a <hi>Rock;</hi> and therefore when he went away, he left St. <hi>Peter</hi> his Succeſſor, and gave him the ſame Name, becauſe he was to be the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Prince of the Church; even ſuch a Foundation of it, againſt which the Gates of Hell ſhould not prevail. Then he adds, that by the Keys, Chriſt gave the fulneſs of all Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Power only to St. <hi>Peter:</hi> VVhich Power, is to open and ſhut the Kingdom of Heaven, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by it is meant Life Eternal, or the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Militant Church. VVhich power of the Keys is greater, as given to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> than to the reſt of the Apoſtles: The power of bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and looſing is a partial and inferior Power which they have; but his is to Govern, to Teach, to Diſpoſe, and Exerciſe all things which belong to the Office of General Paſtor. For, as a King in his Kingdome hath the Sword given to him alone, but he commits the uſe of it to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Magiſtrates: ſo St. <hi>Peter</hi> hath the Power of the Keys commited to him properly and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, but transfers the uſe of them in ſome inferior manner, to Paſtors of a lower Rank, that are ſubſtituted by him.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Remiſh</hi> Tranſlation, that we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how great ſtreſs they put upon theſe words, they are decyphered in a diſtinct Character; and are rendred remarkable by being appointed the Goſpel for ſo many Feſtivals, as for St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s day, for the <hi>Cathedra Petri Romae, Jan.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp; Antiochiae. Feb.</hi> 22. for the Feaſt of <hi>Petri ad Vincula. Aug.</hi> 1. and on the day of the Creation and Coronation of the Pope, and on the Anniverſary thereof. What is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41377:9"/>to be found in their Annotations, more than what the Gentlemen already named have hinted, is not much: Only they are angry with the Engliſh Tranſlators for not rendring the words thus. <hi>Thou art a</hi> Rock, <hi>and upon this</hi> Rock; or, <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter; or, <hi>Upon this</hi> Peter <hi>I will build my Church.</hi> VVhich if it be a fault, is likewiſe to be found in their ſo much adored vulgar Tranſlation. In the Expoſition of the Keys, they enlarge St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Power, by aſcribing to him the Authority and Chair of Doctrine, Knowledg, Judgment, and Diſcretion between true and falſe Doctrine: The height of Government, the power of making Laws, of calling Councils, of the principal Voice in them, of Confirming them, of making Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and wholſome Decrees, of Abrogating the contrary, of Ordaining Biſhops and Paſtors, or depoſing or ſuſpending them; finally, the Power to diſpenſe the Goods of the Church, both Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal: and therefore by the Name of <hi>Keyes,</hi> is given that Super-eminent Power, which is called in reſpect of the Power granted to other Apoſtles, Biſhops, and Paſtors, <hi>plenitudo Poteſtatis,</hi> fulneſs of Power.</p>
            <p>This is that Expoſition on which the Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates for the <hi>Popes</hi> Supremacy lay ſo great ſtreſs, that they can by no means afford us any other; it is the grand ſupport of the Holy Chair, the very bottom of all <hi>Papal</hi> Authority; for, on what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Rock</hi> other parts of the Chriſtian Church are founded, yet this we are aſſured of, that the Roman is built upon this, and the greatneſs of it's Biſhop muſt ſink, if we take away this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prop of it.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:41377:9"/>
            <p> By ſuch meanes are the Waters of Life trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, but not by good Angels; not to heal the VVounds, and make up the breaches of the Church, but to vex and widen them; and when the Fountain is rendred ſo muddy, we muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing but putrid ſtreams. It is a great Argument of a ſinking Cauſe, when men catch at Straws for their ſupport. And we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the Scriptures are altogether ſilent in their Cauſe, when upon this one Foundation, they raiſe ſo many Structures, as the Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the <hi>Pope,</hi> the Infallibility and Viſibility of their Church, and the Power of Indulgences; All which muſt of neceſſity fall to the Ground, if the <hi>Rock</hi> on which they be Built, be removed.</p>
            <p n="2">II. As it is certainly in our following Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (the ſecond thing propos'd) whereby the Scriptures ſhall be ſo far vindicated from the ſenſe already put on them, to which they are rackt, that they ſhall ſpeak in their own proper Language, and in it deliver Truth openly and clearly.</p>
            <p>There are (as you remember) ſeveral Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions concerning the <hi>Rock</hi> in the <hi>Text.</hi> The firſt whereof is, that <hi>Peter</hi> is the <hi>Rock,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Bellarmine</hi> proves by the Authority of ſome Fathers, I ſhall take off their Teſtimony: The Authorities are, St. <hi>Cyril. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>com. in Jo.</hi> That upon <hi>Peter,</hi> as on a firm <hi>Rock,</hi> his Church ſhould be built. The Next is St. <hi>Hilary, (In hunc Locum).</hi> Oh happy Foundation of the Church, in impoſing thy new Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The laſt is St. <hi>Baſil,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41377:10"/>(lib. de poenit.)</hi> Tho <hi>Peter</hi> be a <hi>Rock,</hi> yet he is not a <hi>Rock</hi> as Chriſt is: For, Chriſt is the true and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable <hi>Rock</hi> of himſelf: <hi>Peter</hi> is unmovable by Chriſt the <hi>Rock.</hi> Now we confeſs with <hi>Cyril, Hilary,</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> that <hi>Peter</hi> was a Stone, deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Foundation of the Church, but ſo as all the Apoſtles are Stones, upon which the Church is Builded, (<hi>Rev.</hi> 21.14.) And though we are taught by the Apoſtles (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.) That other Foundation can no man lay, than that is laid, which is Jeſus Chriſt: Yet we do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Miniſtery and Laborers of his Apoſtles, whom alſo we acknowledg to be Stones and Foundations of his Church; not in reſpect of their Perſons, but of their Heavenly Doctrine, whereby they became, with the Prophets, the Foundation, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt being the Corner Stone,</hi> Epheſ. 2.20.</p>
            <p>So that we can ſafely allow, that <hi>Peter</hi> may be ſtiled, the <hi>Rock</hi> on which the Church is built, if we take it in a qualified and Secundary ſenſe: He is that Apoſtle on whom (in the Planting of the Church, as on a chief ſtone in the Building) there is great ſtreſs and weight laid: He was already one of the moſt conſiderable Diſciples of Chriſt, ſharing with <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> in many ſignal Favors which others enjoyed not: He twice made Confeſſion with greateſt Alacrity and firmeſt boldneſs, of Chriſt's being the Meſſias, and the Son of God: He firſt made known both to Jews and Gentiles the Truth of that which he here profeſſes, <hi>that Jeſus is the Chriſt.</hi> And as amongſt the Hebrews all the Levites were in a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41377:10"/>common Notion of this Phraſe, called Stones of the Temple: ſo he is called by way of Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, ſuch a Stone, as relying on the Corner Stone, was with the Reſt of the Apoſtles a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Stone in the Building of Chriſt; yet not ſo, as excluding the reſt of the Apoſtles from that Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge; as is already ſaid, and ſhall be in its place proved. Now ſhould we grant (as in this ſenſe we may, without any prejudice to our own Cauſe) That St. <hi>Peter</hi> is the <hi>Rock,</hi> on which the Church is built; yet it availes the Gentlemen of <hi>Rome</hi> but little, towards the Maintenance of their pretended Supremacy.</p>
            <p>But there are other Opinions concerning this <hi>Rock,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Videſis St.</hi> Ignat. <hi>Ep. ad</hi> Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delph. <hi>St.</hi> Greg. Nyſſ. <hi>de Trin. adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Judaeos. St.</hi> Iſid. Peluſ. <hi>Epiſt. lib.</hi> i. <hi>ep.</hi> 235. <hi>B.</hi> Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. <hi>in Can. St.</hi> Greg. <hi>Epiſt. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ep.</hi> 33. Theoph. <hi>in</hi> Mat. 16. <hi>St.</hi> Aug. <hi>in Ep. St.</hi> Joh. <hi>Tract.</hi> 10. <hi>St.</hi> Baſ. <hi>Seleuc. Orat.</hi> 25. <hi>St.</hi> Jacob. <hi>Liturg.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 26, <hi>&amp;c. And ſome which joyn the Perſon of St.</hi> Peter, <hi>profeſs it is</hi> Propter Robur Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſionis. Juſtin Martyr <hi>Dial. cum</hi> Tryph. <hi>St.</hi> Chryſoſt. <hi>Hom.</hi> 2. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 50. <hi>St.</hi> Ambroſ. <hi>Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>in St.</hi> Luc. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>And St.</hi> Gregory <hi>gives it for a Rule, When</hi> Petra <hi>is read in the Singular Number (and ſo it is here)</hi> Chriſtus eſt, <hi>Chriſt is ſignifyed.</hi>
               </note> which will give us a more clear and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous Senſe of the Place: One of them is <hi>Calvin</hi>'s, (Inſtit. Lib.) <hi>That the Rock is Chriſt:</hi> As if Chriſt had ſaid; <hi>Upon this Rock, that is, my Self;</hi> pointing out, as it were, himſelf unto them; as when he ſaid, <hi>Deſtroy this Temple,</hi> Joh. 2.19. So that, the Miſtake of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> in one Caſe, ſeems not to be leſs Partial or Willful, than that of the <hi>Jews</hi> in the other. <hi>That this</hi> Rock <hi>is Chriſt, is manifeſt</hi> (ſayes <hi>Chemnitius</hi>) <hi>from divers places in Scripture, in which the Name of a</hi> Rock <hi>is aſcribed to Chriſt, or to the Lord:</hi> As <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.18. <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41377:11"/>18.3. &amp; 31.3. And Chriſt is called, <hi>The only Foundation,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.11. &amp; 1 Pet. 2.6. That our Saviour ſeems to refer to theſe Words in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 28.16. <hi>Behold! I lay in</hi> Sion <hi>for a Foundation, a Stone, a Tryed Stone, a precious Corner Stone, a Sure Foundation;</hi> is the Judgement of Dr. <hi>Lightfoot, (Her. Heb.</hi> in <hi>Locum.</hi>) So that, when St. <hi>Peter</hi> firſt of all declared the Myſtery of the Incarnation, and Deity of Chriſt; the Diſciples were taught out of the Prophet, who was that Stone that was laid in <hi>Syon</hi> for a Foundation, never to be thrown down; which was therefore ſo Firm, becauſe he was not a Creature, but the Son of God: Which Sir-name <hi>Peter</hi> obtained; not that he was that Stone, but that he ſhould have great Concern in building the Church upon it.</p>
            <p>The other Senſe of the <hi>Rock,</hi> is, That the Church is built on the Faith of <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof then made: Which Opinion is by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> aſcribed to <hi>Luther;</hi> and <hi>by his Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſtands Eſtabliſhed by the AUthority of many Fathers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hil.</hi> lib. 6. <hi>De Trin.</hi> ſayes; Upon the <hi>Rock</hi> of this Confeſſion, the Church is built: This Faith is the Foundation of the Church: By this Faith, are the Gates of Hell weakned: This Faith hath the Keys of the Kingdome of Heaven. <hi>Ambr.</hi> lib. 6. cap. 9. <hi>in Luc. Fundamentum Eccleſiae Fides eſt. Chryſoſt.</hi> Hom. 55. <hi>in Mat. Upon this Rock will I build my Church;</hi> That is, Upon this Faith and Confeſſion. <hi>Cyril Alex.</hi> lib. 4. <hi>De Trin.</hi> The <hi>Rock</hi> (as I take it) is nothing elſe, but the firm and unſhaken Faith of the Diſciple: <hi>In quâ Ecoleſia Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41377:11"/>ita fundata &amp; firmata eſſet, ut non laberetur,</hi> &amp;c. For, were the Church founded upon St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and not rather upon the Confeſſion he had made, it had preſently Faln: For, <hi>Peter</hi> ſtumbled at the Article of our Saviour's Paſſion immediately after the Text, and was Rebuked by the Name of <hi>Satan:</hi> And <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. he thrice denyed Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, Becauſe the Church is uſually in Scripture called the Temple and Houſe of God (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16.) which reſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one unmovable Foundation, and is raiſed by the joyning together of Living Stones, Chriſt therefore uſes the Metaphorical Word, <hi>I will Build.</hi> As he is ſaid to deſtroy, who alienates mens Minds from the Truth to believe a Lye, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates them from the Church; ſo he is ſaid to Build, who reconciles men to it, and gains Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereto by Preaching the Word.</p>
            <p>Were there ſo much Myſtery in the Promiſe, as they of <hi>Rome</hi> pretend; that becauſe Chriſt (who always was, and ever will be the Foundation and Head of the Church) ſays in the future, <hi>I will Build;</hi> therfore, St. <hi>Peter</hi> muſt needs be the <hi>Rock,</hi> on which it will be Built: It ſhould have been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the ſame Reaſon; <hi>Not my, but thy Church;</hi> Becauſe Chriſt had a Church, before this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſhould be accompliſht. But there are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Reaſons to be given, why Chriſt ſays, <hi>I will Build my Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. Comparing it to the Church he had before; becauſe after Chriſt's Aſcenſion, the Light of the Goſpel ſhone clearer; &amp; thoſe things were Revealed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41377:12"/>and brought to open view, which before had been wrapt up in Darkneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Becauſe of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who were to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Knowledg of the Goſpel of Chriſt, and to be made one Sheepfold under the great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, and Biſhop of their Souls.</p>
            <p>The next Phraſe is, <hi>And the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it.</hi> The Chriſtian Church ſhall be ſo founded, and ſo Built, that the Power of Hell, Death, and the Grave, ſhall not get the Victory over it: It ſhall be ſo Planted and Watred by <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, that God ſhall give it an eternal Increaſe; it ſhall never be deſtroyed. The Church thus Eſtabliſht, may be underſtood either as it ſignifies Particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Believers, true faithful Chriſtians, of which the Church conſiſts: and tho theſe ſhall die, yet Death ſhall have no Dominion over them; Chriſt ſhall break open the Bars, and caſt thoſe Cords from them, and ſhall reſcue them by his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the power of the Grave. Or, <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> The Church may be taken for the whole Congregation of Chriſtian Profeſſors, and then this promiſe ſecures it from the Gates of Hell, ſo as it ſhall never periſh totally, or irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; It is inexpugnable, and ſhall remain for ever; and whatever Change it ſuffers in the World, it ſhall again lift up its Head, which is truly and effectually performed, if, as it decays or periſhes in one Branch or Part, it revives or flouriſh in another. Nay, ſhould it at ſome one time (as Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> obſerves; tho neither he nor we lay any great ſtreſs upon it,) be quite extinct, yet <hi>the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41377:12"/>Gates of Hell have not prevailed againſt it,</hi> if it ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes again Victorious: As the Enemy is not ſaid to have prevailed againſt a Town, if it be ever recovered out of his Hands.</p>
            <p>The 19. v. <hi>And I will give unto thee the Keys</hi> &amp;c. is capable of this Interpretation: That the <hi>Keyes</hi> are the Word of God, whereby the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven is opened, <hi>i. e.</hi> Remiſſion of ſins and Eternal Life is promiſed, to thoſe that Believe and Repent; or ſhut, when Pardon and Life are denyed to the Impenitent and Unbelievers. <hi>Peter</hi> binds when he inflicts puniſhment, as Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, Penance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or refers to the dreadful Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God; he looſes, when he remits thoſe Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and declares the ſinner Abſolved: And this judgment paſt on Earth, if according to the Rule propoſed, the Word of God, is ratified, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in Heaven; To explain this Power here conferred, Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> gives us the Form of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> which was in theſe or the like words; <hi>Receive thou Power to Bind, or to Looſe:</hi> So Chriſt, when he confers on the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles the Miniſterial Function, Commands them to bind and to looſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> to Teach what is to be done, or not to be done; as will appear, if you will obſerve with the ſame Author, that this Power extends only to Things, not to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: So that according to him, this is the ſenſe of the Place. The time is coming (ſays Chriſt) when the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall be in part abrogated, and in part continued: ſo that to <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Apoſtles Power is granted to confirm or aboliſh, what ſeems good unto the Holy Ghoſt, and unto
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41377:13"/>them: As they forbad Circumciſion and other Rites (<hi>Acts</hi> 15.28, 29.) and permitted <hi>Paul</hi> to purify himſelf, (<hi>Acts</hi> 21.24.) and the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor will not allow this power of Binding and Looſing, to import as much as that given, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.23. of Remitting and Retaining ſins. For there (ſayes he) it is treated of the Perſons to be, or not to be, Puniſhed; Here of Doctrines and things Lawful or Prohibited, that are ſubject to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the Apoſtles. But we muſt crave leave to differ from the judgment of this Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Reverend Author; and declare with <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, lib. Inſt. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. §. 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. §. 1. That Chriſt explained what He meant by binding and looſing, when He gave the Apoſtles Authority to to remit or retain Sins. He is ſaid to remit ſins, who, by Preaching the Goſpel, <hi>converts</hi> men to God; he is ſaid to Retain, who declares, that the <hi>obſtinate ſinner</hi> is reſerved for everlaſting Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: From whence it follows, To receive the Keyes of the Kingdom of Heaven, is not to be promoted to any Principality or Power over o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but the Miniſtry of the Word: Which is approved by St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> when he ſayes, That the <hi>Apoſtles do Looſe men by the Word of God, by the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Scriptures, and by the Word of Exhortation.</hi> Which Senſe is ſafe and plain; and with the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction here implyed, and by <hi>Calvin</hi> not exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, is the entire meaning of the Place.</p>
            <p>For the Power of Adminiſtring and Ruling the Church of God, the Family of Chriſt, is hereby conferred on the Apoſtles. This primarily and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependently belongs to Chriſt, the Holy and True,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41377:13"/>who hath the Key of <hi>David, Rev.</hi> 3.7. Keyes are confeſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Enſigne of Power; But that Power is not all of one kind; it is Greater or Leſs; Principal and Independent; or Inferior and Derivative: And ſeveral Keyes are Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems of theſe ſeveral Powers. <hi>David</hi> was a King, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent from any on Earth; and conſequently, the Key of <hi>David</hi> notes an Independent Supreme Power; and that applyed to the Church, belongs only to Chriſt. But the Keyes of the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> mentioned (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.22.) to which the Text ſeems to refer, notes an Inferior Power; that of a Steward in <hi>David</hi>'s Family, who being perfectly ſubordinate to him, hath yet the Adminiſtration of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of his Family intruſted to him. Now, Chriſt is the Original, and Prime Fountain of all Power over the whole Church, that Spiritual Kingdom of <hi>David;</hi> as to whom was given, by the Father, all Power in Heaven and Earth; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, that of Looſing or Remitting Sin on Earth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.6. And this is by Chriſt communicated to his Apoſtles, and their Succeſſours, the Biſhops in the Church, as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeveral Stewards: As St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> obſerves; That the Biſhops are thoſe Faithful Servants in the Parable, whom the Lord ſets over his Houſe.</p>
            <p>The Senſe of the Words on both Sides thus given, our Paſſage is clear to the Third and Laſt Thing propoſed: which was to conſider, The Power, Honour, and Priviledges hereby conferred on St. <hi>Peter;</hi> which are,
<list>
                  <item>1. Extraordinary, or Perſonal.</item>
                  <item>2. Ordinary, or to be derived down to his Succeſſours.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. I begin with the Extraordinary Power, Honour, and Priviledges of St. <hi>Peter:</hi> Which I alſo call <hi>Perſonal;</hi> not as Excluding the reſt of the Apoſtles, but their Succeſſours.</p>
            <p>In Diſcourſing of which, I ſhall lay down theſe Two Things:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:41377:14"/> 1. VVhat the Extraordinary Power, Honour, and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of an Apoſtle are; of which the ſucceeding Church did not partake.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in theſe Things, St. <hi>Peter</hi> hath no Superiority o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the other Apoſtles; But that they were all Equal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I am to ſhew, what the Extraordinary and Perſonal Power, Honour, and Priviledge of an Apoſtle is.</p>
            <p>Chriſt, while he had his Reſidence on Earth, did not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Government of his Church into the Hands of others; but Exerciſed the Office of Apoſtle and Biſhop, in his own Perſon: Which Stile is given him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25. But that he might ſhew himſelf Faithful in the Houſe of God; before he was to leave the World, and return back to Heaven, he did Ordain and Conſtitute ſeveral Officers, who might in his Abſence, Conduct and Over-ſee the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Church; accordingly therefore, <hi>He gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers; For the the gathering together of the Saints, the Work of the Miniſtry, and the Edifying of the Body of Chriſt; Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til we all meet in the Unity of the Faith, and Knowledge of the Son of God into a Perfect Man, even into the Meaſure of the Age of the Fulneſs of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 2.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Amongſt theſe, the Apoſtles were Chief and Principal; and as far in Office as Honour, before all other Orders of the Church: Having theſe Badges of their Power and Priviledges, not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable to any other Miniſters of Chriſt: <hi>Immediate Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and <hi>Election; Infallibility of Judgement,</hi> in delivering the Doctrines of the Kingdome of Heaven; <hi>Generality of Commiſſion,</hi> comprehending all Places and Perſons; The <hi>Gift of Tongues,</hi> enabling them to ſpeak in all the Languages of the World, and the Knowledge of all Secrets, and Power to confirm their Doctrines by Signes and Miracles,; and by the Impoſition of their Hands, the Power of Beſtowing the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41377:14"/>Miraculous Gifts of the Spirit to Others. Theſe Powers and Privileges, even in the Times of the Apoſtles, were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on Any but Themſelves: The Evangeliſts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets were not called Immediately by Chriſt, but appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Apoſtles; neither were they led Infallibly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Truth: General Commiſſion they had not; but were taken into the Fellowſhip of the Apoſtles Labours, to Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt their Preſence, and Supply their Abſence; to Build up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Foundation, and to Perfect what they Began. And tho the Miraculous Gifts of Tongues, and Working Miracles, were not proper to the Apoſtles; yet having them in ſuch ſort, as by the Impoſition of their Hands to Give the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Enabling others to VVork Miracles, was Peculiar and Proper to them. Hence it is, that St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> concludes; That, tho Prophecy, the Gift of Miracles, and Expelling Devils, the Orders of Paſtors and Teachers, were all Spiritual Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Enſignes of great Authority; yet the Apoſtolical Eminency is far above all theſe: VVhich therefore he calls, a <hi>Spiritual Conſulſhip:</hi> An Apoſtle having as great Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, above all other Officers in the Church; as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul had, above all other Magiſtrates in <hi>Rome.</hi> Theſe were a few Select Men, whom our Lord choſe out of the reſt of his Diſciples; to devolve Part of the Government on their Shoulders, and to Depute them for the firſt Planting and Settling Chriſtianity in the VVorld: He choſe Twelve, whom he named <hi>Apoſtles, (Luk.</hi> 6.13.) whom he Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Extraordinary Gifts, that they might more preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently contend againſt the ſtrong Prejudices of Pleaſure and Intereſt. The Power of Tongues, and other Miraculous Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions of the Holy Ghoſt, being like VVatering to a Plant; which, when it hath taken Root, and filled the Land, could Subſiſt without thoſe Extraordinary Helps. VVhen <hi>Iſrael</hi> was brought into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> into a Strange Land,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41377:15"/>God in a moſt ſignal manner Fought againſt the Nations; and Diſpoſſeſt them: But when his People were ſettled there, God ſends them not, even in their greateſt Diſtreſs, ſuch Remarkable Deliverances, as he did before. So Chriſt, in the Eſtabliſhment of his Church, obſerves the ſame Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Providence: The Powers of the Devil, when free and inſtigating all Mankind againſt the Doctrine of Chriſt, muſt be Reſiſted and Oppoſed by a Power ſuperior to his own: But when he was once Subdued by Chriſt, and then by his Church, there needs not the ſame Power to keep him in Bonds, as at firſt to Conquer and Fetter him. He may ſtill rage, and ſhake his Chain; but he cannot break it. He looks Terribly, like the Souldiers of <hi>Tarentum</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> when they lay Dead with their Swords in their Hands: He may affright, but he cannot Hurt. So that, in this caſe, the Holy Ghoſt acts not ſo Extraordinarily to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, as at firſt to Plant it; becauſe he that Oppoſes it, is not now ſo Strong as he then was: For, a leſs Force can keep the Garriſon, than take the City. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> gives a good Reaſon (<hi>De Util. Credendi,</hi> cap. 16.) why it was not fit, that theſe Miraculous Courſes ſhould ſtill have continued; <hi>Becauſe the Livelineſs of the Spring, after a Dead Winter, is no Wonder, ſince acted every Year: So the Strangeneſs of Miracles, which moved at firſt, would not now be regarded, if continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Power and Honour of the Apoſtle-ſhip, conveyed by the Commiſſion to the Apoſtles, was equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on all; (which is my Second Conſideration). They were all Choſen in the ſame Manner, and at the ſame Time: All equally Infallible in their Judgements, and Determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; All ſent to Preach, and Baptize all Nations, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the Power of <hi>Binding</hi> and <hi>Looſing;</hi> and All fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with the neceſſary Gifts and Powers of the Holy Ghoſt.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41377:15"/>Indeed, the Fortunes of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> depend upon a different Doctrine; and the Tide of its Intereſt runs ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way: and it behoves the Patrons of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, to contend with mighty Zeal and Fierceneſs for St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s: For, if the Original Right be queſtioned, that which is derived from it muſt fall, when it loſes its Foundation.</p>
            <p>There is nothing ſo certain, as that Men want Good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, when they urge VVeak Ones: and none but a Fool will Build his Houſe upon the Sands, that hath a Rock at hand for a Foundation: So that, when we hear <hi>Bellarmine</hi> recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning up ſuch Prerogatives of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as theſe are; The Change of his Name, The Fiſhing in his Ship, Paying Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute for Chriſt and Himſelf; and ſuch like: We may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; That he hath proved nothing but the Weakneſs of the Cauſe he maintains. Indeed, there is one Argument, which is as Uncharitable as it is VVeak: When St. <hi>Peter</hi> hath this Promiſe, <hi>That the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him;</hi> By it the Cardinal underſtands, not only the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Stability of the Univerſal Church; but of the <hi>Rock</hi> on which it is Founded: So that, by a Special Priviledge, it is promiſed to <hi>Peter,</hi> That his Sea ſhall never fail: Which Promiſe, had it been made to the reſt of the Apoſtles; St. <hi>James</hi>'s Seat had been ſtill at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> St. <hi>John</hi>'s at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> St. <hi>Mathews</hi> in <hi>Aethopia;</hi> and St. <hi>Andrews</hi> in <hi>Scythia:</hi> But all theſe have yielded to the Gates of Hell. VVere this a ſafe and honeſt way of Defending a Cauſe, the Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Villain is ever ſecure from the Imputation of Guilt: and Succeſs is as good an Argument for the great <hi>Turk</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> as for the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we conſult the Fathers, they tell us, That all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were Equal, as having equal Power committed to them in the Keys: Tho it be ſaid to St. <hi>Peter</hi> only in this Place; <hi>That upon this Rock</hi>  and, <hi>To thee I give</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41377:16"/>Yet in another Place, the ſame Charge is committed to all the Apoſtles, (as <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.) And all of them Receive the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven; and the Stability of the Church is fixt upon them All; <hi>(Hieronym.)</hi> Chriſt after his Reſurrection gave Equal Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to all his Apoſtles; and ſaid to them all, <hi>Whoſe Sins ye Remit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Cyprian:</hi> And in another Place; What <hi>Peter</hi> was, that were the reſt of the Apoſtles; having a Fellowſhip of the ſame Honour and Power. <hi>Theophylact</hi> alſo intimates; That the Church may be ſaid to be Built upon <hi>Peter,</hi> but no otherwiſe than upon the reſt of the Apoſtles: And he adds; They who have obtained the Grace to be Biſhops, have Power to Remit and Bind, as well as <hi>Peter:</hi> For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho it were ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, <hi>I will give to thee</hi>  yet the Keys were granted to all the Apoſtles. This was the Doctrine of the Primitive Church; To which agrees the Judgement of a <hi>Pope</hi> in thoſe Times, (<hi>Greg. Epiſt. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 34, 38.) who was very ſevere upon the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> for affecting a Supremacy over the whole Church: And ſo little did he think of putting in his own Plea, that he Condemns it, as Intrenching upon the Prerogative of Chriſt. To theſe Authorities, which plainly deſtroy the <hi>Roman</hi> Cauſe, there muſt be ſome Anſwers given by <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> and <hi>Stapleton;</hi> which are very indifferent, tho the beſt they could afford: <hi>Stapleton</hi> tells us, That the ſame Power is not conferred by <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. &amp; <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. as in my Text: Which St. <hi>Jerome</hi> affirms, and we have already proved. To the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Part of St. <hi>Jerem</hi>'s Teſtimony, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> grants, That all the Apoſtles are equally the Foundation of the Church; but they as Meſſengers and Ambaſſadors, <hi>Peter</hi> as Ordinary Paſtor: What he means, ſhall be preſently conſidered. Thus he alſo endeavours to ſilence St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Teſtimony, by telling us; That the Apoſtles were all Equal in reſpect of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41377:16"/>Chriſtian People, having all the ſame Authority over them; but were not Equal amongſt themſelves, St. <hi>Peter</hi> being Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to the reſt. Out of theſe Anſwers, and other their Writings concerning this Matter, we may gather theſe three Differences betwixt St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the Apoſtleſhip, all the Apoſtles were Equal: But <hi>Peter</hi> received this Plenary Power, not as Apoſtle, but as Ordinary Paſtor, and Biſhop of the Church; which was to continue to his Succeſſours.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtles were Equal in reſpect of the Nations to be Converted by them; but not in reſpect of Themſelves. All the Apoſtles had Supreme Authority over the Chriſtian VVorld: But <hi>Peter</hi> was ſo Supreme Head of all Chriſtians, that he was alſo Superior to the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All the Apoſtles had Equal Power of Executing what Chriſt commanded them: But St. <hi>Peter</hi> only had Power of making New Orders; and preſcribing, by his Succeſſors, what is alwayes to be done in the Church.</p>
            <p>Which Pretences we ſhall now Examine, and Confute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is pretended, that the Amplitude of Power, which all the Apoſtles had in common, the reſt had only for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and as a Priviledge meerly Perſonal, was to end with them. But <hi>Peter</hi> had the ſame in ſuch ſort, that he might leave it to his Succeſſours: So that, that Power which in the reſt was Apoſtolical and Temporary, was Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, Paſtoral, and Perpetual in <hi>Peter:</hi> Which, were it True, then every <hi>Pope</hi> is immediately Choſen by God, not by the Cardinals. Then they are all Conſecrated, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Immediately by Chriſt, not by Biſhops: Then have they all Power to write Books of Canonical Scripture; and are free from Danger of Erring, whenſoever they either Preach or Write: Then can they confirm their Doctrine by Miracles, and give the Holy Ghoſt by the Impoſition of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41377:17"/>their Hands. But ſince no <hi>Pope</hi> can pretend, without great Impiety to any of theſe Preheminencies; it is vain for them to urge, That ſome part of that Dignity and Power that was in <hi>Peter,</hi> is in <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſours; for ſo there is in the meaneſt Prieſt in the VVorld.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As for that other Shift; That the Apoſtles were Equal towards the People, but not amongſt themſelves; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch, as they had no Superiour, in reſpect of their Office of Teaching and Governing the VVorld; but were ſubject to one Head, in reſpect of their Perſonal Actions: It is one of the ſtrongeſt Paradoxes, the VVorld ever heard of. For, who can imagine, that God would truſt the Apoſtles with the managing the weightyeſt Affairs of his Church, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the whole VVorld, without being any way accountant in reſpect thereof, unto any one amongſt them as Superiour; and that he would appoint an Head and Chief, and ſubject them to his Cenſure in their Perſonal Actions? But this is not the only Abſurdity, this Doctrine runs them into:</p>
            <p>For, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They tell us; That all the Apoſtles had E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Power of Executing what Chriſt commanded them: But St. <hi>Peter</hi> only had Authority to make New Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to preſcribe by his Succeſſors, what is alwayes to be done in the Church. But this is ſaid, without any Proof at all; and indeed, is a Matter of another Debate; Of which, I have now thus much to ſay; That it doth not appear, That <hi>Peter</hi> had Power of himſelf, to Determine any Matter of Moment: Elſe, when he was queſtion'd for going unto the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> he needed not to have made his Defence before the Apoſtles, and Brethren; but would have ſtrengthned his Practice by his own Authority. And at the Great Council at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he neither preſided as Chief; nor was his Vote more Requiſite, than any other Apoſtle's, for the Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what they then Determined.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:41377:17"/>
            <p> The Apoſtles were all Stars of the greateſt Magnitude, and had each of them a Light to guide men to Chriſt in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary concerns of Chriſtianity: But when any momentous matter ariſes in debate, They then are gathered together, and make up a glorious Conſtellation, which by its illuſtrious emanations of Light, leads the Church in its darkeſt emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies. By whoſe Acts and Writings, the Church is ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from Error, and directed into all Truth, that it no longer needs the extraordinary ways of Guidance: If men would ſubmit to the Truths, they find, there is no want of any power of defining new Articles of Faith. The Church cannot, by her Approbation, make thoſe Aſſertions and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to be Catholick Verities, that were not ſo before: She may indeed propoſe what was before not ſo throughly thought on. But it is not the Authority of the Church, but the clear deduction from the things which we are bound ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presſly to believe, that maketh things of that Sort, that they muſt be particularly and diſtinctly Known and Believed, that were not neceſſarily ſo to be Believed before.</p>
            <p>I conclude this part, with the judgment of the <hi>magdebur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes, (Cen.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.) who prove, That there is no Supremacy given to St. <hi>Peter</hi> by this place, becauſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles (<hi>Mat.</hi> 18.) afterwards doubted who was the greateſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. And it is Reaſonable to ſuppoſe, that Chriſt would have commanded them to ſtrive no more about it, had he appointed St. <hi>Peter</hi> to be their Chief; His ſilence herein is Argument enough.</p>
            <p n="2">II. I come now to the Ordinary Power, Honour, and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Apoſtles; which were to be deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved down to their Succeſſors.</p>
            <p>That it is Eſſential to the being and conſtitution of a Church, not only that there ſhould be a diſtinction of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy and Laity; but that in the Clergy alſo there ſhould be different Orders, is demonſtrable from Scripture, Antiquity,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41377:18"/>and the general Concurrence of the Church in all Ages: Tho indeed for the Reaſons before-given, it is not neceſſary that the Miniſters of the Goſpel ſhould in every Age have the ſame qualifications the Apoſtles had: For as thoſe were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved as peculiar and proper unto the Apoſtles, and not Communicated to any other in their time; ſo are they not paſſed over to their After-comers by Succeſſion: But in place of Immediate Calling, we have now Succeſſion: Inſtead of Infallibility of Judgment, the direction of their Writings, guiding us in the ſearch of Truth. There is now no gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Commiſſion, but a particular Aſſignation to Biſhops and Paſtors, of ſeveral Churches to rule, and parts of Chriſt's Flock to Feed: Inſtead of Miraculous Gifts, and the Apoſtles Power to confer them, there are planted and ſettled amongſt us, Schools and Univerſities, fitting men for the Work of the Miniſtry. In place of their Miracles, wherewith they Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to the Senſes of men, in eſtabliſhing the Chriſtian Doctrine; we are Educated and brought up in the Faith, and have it by ſo many Generations recommended to us, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed at firſt by the Apoſtles Miracles. So that we ſee, how the Apoſtles extraordinary Gifts, which were moſt neceſſary for the planting of the Church, are changed in reſpect of their Succeſſors: But the ſtanding, and perpetual part of their Office, was to Teach and Inſtruct the People in the Principles and Duties of Religion, to Adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to confer Orders by the Impoſition of Hands, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute and appoint Guides and Officers, who ſhould Bind and Looſe Sinners by Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures; and finally to exerciſe the Diſcipline and Government of the Church. And in theſe they are Succeeded by the ordinary Rulers, and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick Guides, who are to ſuper-intend and diſcharge the Affairs and Offices of the Church to the end of the World. It is not my Buſineſs at preſent, to defend the different Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41377:18"/>of the Church, from the Cavils of thoſe, whoſe Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, or Malice, would bury it in Confuſion: Neither am I concerned to prove the Succeſſion of Paſtors againſt them, who (by pretence of an immediate and extraordinary Call) leap into, and invade the Offices of the Church; Theſe are not the men with whom I now intend. I ſhall prove, That the Pope (as St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor) hath none of thoſe Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Gifts, which will qualifie him for the Oecumenical Paſtorſhip: For granting not only that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome,</hi> but that he was Biſhop there, &amp; that for Five &amp; Twenty years together, (tho the Antients attribute the founding, the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy and Government of that Church equally to <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> making the one as much concerned in it as the other); yet what would this make for the unlimited ſoveraignty and univerſality of that Church, unleſs a better Evidence could be produced, than this Succeſſion to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> for its uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulable Supremacy and Dominion over the whole Chriſtian World? For had not the ſame <hi>Peter</hi> a Succeſſor at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and the other Apoſtles in their ſeveral Sees; and yet none of theſe pretended, tho they ſeem to have equal Right, to this Power. But here we are told, That immediate Vocation, the ſeeing Chriſt in the Fleſh, power to write Canonical Books of Scripture, and other priviledges, extraordinarily conferred on the Apoſtles, were fitting to the firſt beginnings of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and ſo not of Perpetual uſe and Neceſſity: But that Univerſality of Juriſdiction, and a kind of Infallibility of Judgment are perpetually neceſſary; and therefore theſe were to paſs from <hi>Peter</hi> to Others, tho the reſt of the Apoſtolick Pre-eminencies were not: Which I ſhall examine, and then conclude. That the <hi>Roman</hi> is a Patriarchal Church, and the Biſhop of it hath Prime Place amongſt other Biſhops of the World, would never be denyed him, would he reſt contented with that: But it muſt by no means be granted, that he is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41377:19"/>an Univerſal Biſhop, having Juriſdiction over the whole Church; that is, ſuch a Biſhop, in whom all Epiſcopal Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, Power, and Authority is Originally Inveſted, from whom it is derived to Others, and who may Limit and Reſtrain the Uſe of it in Others, as ſeemeth good unto Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: For every Biſhop hath, in his place and keeping in his proper Station, the Epiſcopal Power and Authority immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from Chriſt; which is not to be Limited and Reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any, but by the Company and Suffrages of Biſhops: Wherein, tho one be Chief for Order ſake, and to preſerve Unity in the Church; yet he can do nothing without the Concurrence of the Reſt. When the <hi>Conſtantinopolitan Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch</hi> affected this Title, as I before hinted; <hi>Gregory,</hi> then <hi>Pope,</hi> compares him to <hi>Lucifer,</hi> who deſpiſing the Angels, his Companions, ſought to climb up to that Heighth, that he neither might ſeem to be Under any, nor any be found, Over whom he was not.</p>
            <p>As for Infallibility of Judgement, pretended to, as perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and neceſſary in the Church; and as they would have it derived down from St. <hi>Peter</hi> to his Succeſſours at <hi>Rome:</hi> If it be granted to them, that there is a kind of Infallibility, or Non-deficiency rather, in the Univerſal Church; they preſently confound the Notion, and apply it to whom they pleaſe. Accordingly there is this Diſtinction of a Church:</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Church Eſſential, which is the whole Multitude of Believers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Repreſentative; The Aſſembly of Biſhops in a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council, repreſenting the whole Body of the Church from the ſeveral Parts whence they come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Virtual Church, by which they underſtand the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> who being by Chriſt's Appointment, as they ſuppoſe, Chief Paſtor of the whole Church, hath in himſelf Eminently and Virtually as great Certainty of Truth,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41377:19"/>and infallibility of Judgement, as is in the whole Church; upon whom dependeth all that Certainty of Truth that is found in it.</p>
            <p>Of theſe we affirm, That the Church in the firſt Notion, cannot erre or fall away; In the Second, That it may Erre; In the Third, (tho we alſo deny the Notion) That it doth Erre: And againſt Matter of Fact, as I take it, there can be no Proof: Of which, I could give many Inſtances, were it not Loſs of Time to do ſo.</p>
            <p>The Supremacy of the <hi>Pope,</hi> ſo much contended for, and ſo meanly ſupported, is the greateſt Intrenchment in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of it, that was ever made upon the Prerogative of Princes, and the Authority of Biſhops; The Crown and Mitre being ſwallowed up in this Plenitude of Power. So that, it is the Intereſt as well as Duty of Church and State, of Prince and People, of Paſtors and their Flocks, to oppoſe what is ſo much againſt the Wellfare of all Civil and Chriſtian So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties. I ſhall not urge the Inconveniencies only, but the Injuſtice of ſuch a Subjection; whereby all Bonds Natural, Civil, and Chriſtian are broken, if it pleaſe him who uſurps ſuch a Supreme Power over Mens Conſciences: It is the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of God alone, to ſet up his Throne in the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Man; and by the Laws of right Reaſon, to lay ſuch a Reſtraint upon it, as all Humane Powers cannot be able to gain ſay or reſiſt, to cancel or diſanul. Nothing but an expreſs Diſpenſation from God himſelf, can acquit the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject or Child from the Obedience, he ows his Prince or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. Nature, which is God's Law, being herein ſo plain and poſitive, muſt never upon the Interpoſition of any Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Power be tranſgreſt. So that, we muſt be very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to aſſert our own Liberty, and our Superiours Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, againſt that Forreign Prelate, who by his Emiſſaries doth dayly diſturb the Peace of this our <hi>Syon,</hi> and draw off ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41377:20"/>from their Duty and Obedience to God, the Church, their Country, and their Prince.</p>
            <p>Our own Nation is at preſent the Theatre, wherein moſt Hideous Villanies are Plotted and Deſigned; and it is much to be feared, that the Actors are not yet gone off the Stage: And all this, not without a manifeſt Reſpect to, and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Purſuance of, this moſt Pernitious Doctrine: Which is a ſtrong Argument to us, how far blind Zeal can tranſport; and what a wicked Principle can inſpire into their Breaſts, who thus obſtinately adhere to it. For if by ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Power, a King be declared an Heretick, upon that Declaration be Excommunicated, upon that Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be deprived of his Dominions, and Condemned to Death; And if his Subjects at the ſame time be not only abſolved from all Allegiance to him, but bound in Conſcience to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and Deſtroy him, and Execute that direful Sentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Life; What Security can any Prince or People expect from thoſe that maintain ſuch Principles, as tend in ſo direct a Conſequence to the Confuſion and Subverſion of Church and State, when-ever it ſhall pleaſe this Supreme Power to pronounce ſuch a Sentence?</p>
            <p>But ſome have gone farther, and abſolved all Subjects from their Allegiance, if they are reſolved in Conſcience, that their Prince is Heretical. The other is bad enough, I need not trace this any farther.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine (which by them that maintain it, hath been ſometimes accounted Scandalous) is not confined to Theory, but hath been often reduced to Practice: It hath not only been Diſputed of in Schools, but Preach't in Pulpits, maintained in Preſs, and confirmed by Actions. From hence is apprehended all our Danger, and from hence ſprings all our Miſchief; That the Subjects of any Prince, or who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe ſhall come under the Protection of his Laws and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41377:20"/>Government (who for the time are to be reckoned Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects) ſhall preſume to own any Power under Heaven Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to him; and by vertue of Commiſſion from that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Power, ſhall endeavour to diſturb and ſubvert the Laws and Government Eſtabliſht. This is the Firſt Mover in the <hi>Roman Sphear,</hi> that hurryes all Inferior Orbs; The Spring that gives Motion to the <hi>Papal Machin;</hi> When this is ſwallowed down, there is nothing can oppoſe or hinder any of the Deſigns of <hi>Rome.</hi> Wherefore, tho other Doctrines are pitcht upon, as more Abſurd; yet in my Judgement, (and I think, I have the Experience of this Nation to confirm the Truth of it) this is of moſt fatal and pernitious Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; And with its Infallibility annext, throws down all that can oppoſe it ſelf againſt the Holy Chair: The latter makes Men ſtick at no Abſurdities; The former encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and commands them to commit all Villanies. Let us therefore fortify our Reaſon againſt the One, and ſtrengthen our Arms againſt the Other: Let us put on the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of God, and with them joyn our Prince's too, that we may be able to ſtand againſt theſe Adverſaries of both; And then we ſhall not only fight with Honour and Praiſe, but come off with Succeſs and Glory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
